בוקר טוב *Boker tov*. Of course at the דף *Daf* we all
mourn the passing of Rivka Haut, funeral's today at 9:00.
Our learning should be לעילוי נשמתה *le'ilui nishmata*. She was really such
an important member of our community, of our דף *Daf* community, of
course of the Orthodox the Jewish community particularly when we read what's
going on these days in terms of עגונות *agunot*, how the situation
keeps on getting getting worse before it's going to get better. So
she did tremendous, tremendous work for them and for just so many
people. So may her may her memory always be for a blessing.
אמן *Amen*. All right, so we start with the bottom of נ"ה
עמוד ב' *Nun Hey Amud Bet*, the last דף *daf* of סוכה
sukkah *Sukkah*. Oh no, I'm sorry, we did that.
We did that.
Okay.
So we had six
lines from the top on נ"ו עמוד א' *Nun Vav Amud Aleph*.
Okay.
בעצרת אומר לו הילך *Be'atzeret omer lo heilach* etc. So on שבועות
Shavuos *Shavuot* they this is talking about how they would do multiple,
you know,
when they would divide equally the כהנים Kohanim, *Kohanim* and they would
all work together in the בית המקדש Beit Ha-mikdash *Beit Hamikdash* on
the רגלים *Regalim* and they'd all divide the eating of the קרבנות
korbanot *korbanot*. And interestingly, although the עבודה Avodah. *avoda* of the לחם
lechem *lechem*, of the לחם הפנים Lechem HaPanim *Lechem Hapanim* was not
a normal thing, wasn't a unique רגל reghel. *regel* thing and it
was for the as we're going to find out for the for
the regular כהנים kohanim *Kohanim* that exited and that entered would be
the normal division of the לחם הפנים Lechem HaPanim. *Lechem Hapanim*. Nevertheless,
based on a verse, they would divide the לחם הפנים Lechem Hapanim
*Lechem Hapanim* as well. So therefore on שבועות Shavuos *Shavuot* amongst all
the כהנים Kohanim *Kohanim* that gathered for the רגל reghel, *regel*, all
the different groups of the כהנים Kohanim *Kohanim*. So on שבועות Shavuos
*Shavuot* they would divide the לחם הפנים Lechem Hapanim, *Lechem Hapanim* because
it was a רגל reghel. *regel* and they would also divide the
שתי הלחם Shtei HaLechem. *Shtei Halechem* for שבועות Shavuos, *Shavuot* which was
which was חמץ chametz *chametz*. And therefore every כהן kohen, *kohen* would
get a little bit of חמץ chametz *chametz* and a little bit
of מצה matzah *matzah*. So let's take a look. And the
משנה Mishna. *Mishnah* said הילך מצה matzah הילך חמץ chametz *heilach matzah
heilach chametz*. Okay, so notice it mentioned מצה matzah *matzah* first which
was relevant to the more common one, the לחם הפנים Lechem Hapanim
*Lechem Hapanim* before mentioning חמץ chametz. *chametz* which was special to the
חג chag, *chag* that it was שבועות Shavuot *Shavuot*. So now we're
going to get into a fascinating discussion that's almost like something we
maybe should have discussed earlier when we're learning מסכת סוכה Masechet Sukkah,
*Masechet Sukkah*, but the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*, since the end is in
sight here of the מסכת masechet, *masechet*, the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* is
going to discuss it now and tie it into this משנה Mishna.
*Mishnah*. So איתמר *itmar*. רבא *Rava* אמר *amar* סוכה ואחר כך זמן
sukkah ve-achar kach zman. *Sukkah ve'achar kach zman*. When you make the
ברכה bracha. *bracha* at the night, the first night of סוכות Sukkos,
*Sukkot*, first you say לישב בסוכה leishev basukka *leishev basukkah* and then
you say שהחיינו shehecheyanu. *Shehecheyanu*. רבה בר בר חנה Rabba bar bar
Chana *Rabbah bar Bar Chana* אמר *amar* זמן zman, ואחר כך סוכה
sukkah *zman ve'achar kach sukkah*. We say שהחיינו shehecheyanu *Shehecheyanu* and then
you say לישב בסוכה leishev ba-sukkah. *leishev basukkah*. Now I will remind
you that according to the earlier ברייתא Beraita *braita* quoted in the
גמרא Gemara *Gemara*, you're supposed to say שהחיינו shehecheyanu. *Shehecheyanu* when you
build the סוכה sukka. *sukkah*, not only when you go in to
sit on סוכות Sukkot *Sukkot*. But that being said, even already our
practice isn't that way and even already the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* said
that I think it was רבא *Rava*, I forget if one of
the אמוראים Amoraim *Amoraim* would would put it all put them all
together on the כוס *cos* that when you're making קידוש Kiddush, *Kiddush*
on the first night, there he would say the לישב בסוכה leishev
ba-sukkah *leishev basukkah* and the שהחיינו shehecheyanu *Shehecheyanu*, he wouldn't specifically do
it earlier even though that's really the time when you're supposed to.
Again, we don't do that, already in the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* they
weren't doing that, or some weren't doing that. רש"י Rashi *Rashi* says
the scenario is possible you forgot to do it or it's not
your סוכה sukka *sukkah*, you didn't build a סוכה sukka *sukkah*, you're
in somebody else's סוכה sukkah *sukkah*, so you didn't say the שהחיינו
shehecheyanu *Shehecheyanu* earlier, you're saying it this night. And the other thing
to remember is that the שהחיינו Shehecheyanu, *Shehecheyanu* you say at the
night, the first night, has a double duty: one as I said
is the first, the beginning of the מצוה mitzva *mitzvah* of סוכה
sukkah, *sukkah* and therefore that could have been made when you were
building the סוכה sukkah *sukkah*. And the other's the שהחיינו Shehecheyanu *Shehecheyanu*
that you say at the beginning of every יום טוב Yom Tov.
*Yom Tov*, which is about the fact that it's a new it's
a new יום טוב Yom Tov *Yom Tov*. And even though it's
not particularly a new מצוה mitzva *mitzvah* like you'll say a שהחיינו
Shehecheyanu *Shehecheyanu* on שבועות *Shavuot night, not related to any particular מצוה
mitzva *mitzvah* but a שהחיינו Shehecheyanu *Shehecheyanu* on the יום yom. *yom*.
So so here the question is, what is the order between the
שהחיינו Shehecheyanu *Shehecheyanu* and the לישב בסוכה leishev ba-sukkah. *leishev basukkah* focusing
let's say for now on the aspect of the שהחיינו Shehecheyanu *Shehecheyanu*
that is about the מצוה mitzva *mitzvah* of סוכה sukkah *sukkah*. So
therefore does it come after the does it come before. Now you
just reflect for a moment on when we make ברכות *brachot* on
מצוות *mitzvot* and say שהחיינו Shehecheyanu *Shehecheyanu* like הדלקת נרות *hadlakat nerot*
or נטילת לולב lulav *netilat lulav* and we say it after the
ברכת המצוה birkat hamitzvah *birchat hamitzvah*. Okay, but let's see the arguments
here that are both ways. So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says like
this. רבא *Rava* אמר *amar* סוכה sukkah. ואחר כך זמן *Sukkah ve'achar
kach zman*. First you say לישב leishev? *leishev* and then you say
שהחיינו Shehecheyanu? *Shehecheyanu*. חיובא דיומא עדיף *Chiyuva de'yoma adif*. First you do
the obligation of the day, the it starts with the מצוה mitzva,
*mitzvah* of סוכה sukkah *sukkah*. שהחיינו Shehecheyanu *Shehecheyanu* is you know, maybe
it's tangential to it, it's coming as a result of of the
מצוה mitzva *mitzvah* of לישב בסוכה *leishev basukkah*, but you start with
the חיוב *chiyuv* of the day. Also what's unique to the day
is really also what's more significant here, that the לישב בסוכה *leishev
basukkah* is something that is a ברכה bracha *bracha* that is unique
to the fact that it is סוכות Sukkot *Sukkot*, whereas שהחיינו Shehecheyanu,
*Shehecheyanu* has a much more generic ברכה bracha? *bracha*. It's much less
distinctive.
רבה בר בר חנה אמר זמן ואחר כך סוכה. sukkah. Now you
start with שהחיינו. Shehecheyanu Why? תדיר ושאינו תדיר תדיר קודם. tadir vesheino
tadir tadir kodem. I admit שהחיינו Shehecheyanu is broad and abstract and
it applies in many many scenarios. That's why you say it first
because it's the more common ברכה. bracha So here the גמרא Gemara
is framing the issue is: Is it the more distinctive ברכה bracha.
or is it the more regular ברכה? bracha So the גמרא Gemara
says: לימא רב ורבה בר בר חנה בפלוגתא דבית שמאי ובית הלל
קמיפלגי? leima Rav veRabbah bar bar Chana biplugta deBeit Shammai veBeit Hillel
kamifligi? Maybe they are echoing the debate of בית הלל Beit Hillel
and בית שמאי, Beit Shammai, famous debate of בית הלל Beit Hillel
and בית שמאי. Beit Shammai. What is that debate? דתנו רבנן, deTanu
Rabbanan, that our Rabbis taught: דברים שבין בית שמאי ובית הלל בסעודה.
devarim shebein Beit Shammai uBeit Hillel bise'udah. These are a list of
debates between בית הלל Beit Hillel and בית שמאי Beit Shammai as
they relate to a meal. And we're only going to focus on
the first one, there's a whole long list of them. But בית
שמאי אומרים מברך על היום ואחר כך מברך על היין. Beit Shammai
omrim meivarech al hayom ve'achar kach meivarech al hayayin. First you speak
the ברכה bracha. on the day, this is for קידוש, Kiddush. right?
מקדש השבת. Mekadesh HaShabbat. And then you say בורא פרי הגפן. Borei
Peri HaGafen. Not our order obviously. ובית הלל אומרים מברך על היין
ואחר כך מברך על היום. uBeit Hillel omrim meivarech al hayayin ve'achar
kach meivarech al hayom. You start with בורא פרי הגפן Borei Peri
HaGafen and then you say מקדש השבת. Mekadesh HaShabbat. What's the reason
of this debate? So בית שמאי אומרים מברך על היום ואחר כך
מברך על היין. Beit Shammai omrim meivarech al hayom ve'achar kach meivarech
al hayayin. First you do first you do מקדש השבת Mekadesh HaShabbat
and then you say and then you say בורא פרי הגפן. Borei
Peri HaGafen. שהיום גורם ליין שיבא. shehayom goreim leyayin sheyavo. This for
קידוש. Kiddush.
Because the day is the reason you're making קידוש. Kiddush, Right? You
wouldn't be doing בורא פרי הגפן—I Borei Peri HaGafen mean you might
סתם stam because you like to drink wine—but there wouldn't be an
idea of making sure you made a בורא פרי הגפן Borei Peri
HaGafen were it not for the fact that it was שבת. Shabbat.
So you start with the basic anchor what sort of is bringing
about this whole ritual of קידוש, Kiddush. it's מקדש השבת. Mekadesh HaShabbat.
And that's point number one: שהיום גורם ליין שיבא. shehayom goreim leyayin
sheyavo. And number two, just sequentially, chronologically: וכבר קידש היום ועדיין יין
לא בא. uchvar kidesh hayom ve'adayin yayin lo ba.
It becomes שבת Shabbos before you make קידוש. Kiddush So the order
is that way conceptually and chronologically. Of course we can make קידוש
Kiddush. before שבת, Shabbat, you know, we can be מקבל שבת mekabel
Shabbat earlier, but at least in the normal order of things, first
you have first chronologically שבת Shabbat comes first and then you make
קידוש. Kiddush. And in the conceptual order of things, because it's שבת,
Shabbat, that's why you're making קידוש. Kiddush The wine is coming as
a result of שבת. Shabbat. You make מקדש השבת Mekadesh HaShabbat first.
Makes a lot of sense. So let's see what בית הלל Beit
Hillel says. ובית הלל אומרים מברך על היין ואחר כך מברך על
היום. uBeit Hillel omrim meivarech al hayayin ve'achar kach meivarech al hayom.
You start with בורא פרי הגפן. Borei Peri HaGafen. Number one: שהיין
גורם לקידוש שתאמר. shehayayin goreim lekiddush sheteiamer.
It's true you're only saying קידוש Kiddush, because it's שבת. Shabbat. But
what in a way allows you to say קידוש, Kiddush, makes it
קידוש, Kiddush is wine. Now of course as some people might know
it's possible to make קידוש Kiddush, on bread, but fine, then you
would say you say המוציא לחם מן הארץ Hamotzi Lechem Min HaAretz
first. But the point is in order to make this into the
ritual of קידוש, Kiddush. you need some object, you need wine or
bread. So therefore that's what frames this as קידוש. Kiddush, So therefore
that's what comes first. Number one. דבר אחר, davar acher, and another
explanation: ברכת היין תדירה. birchat hayayin tedira.
The בורא פרי הגפן Borei Peri HaGafen is a more common ברכה.
bracha וברכת היום אינה תדירה, uvirchat hayom einah tedira, and the ברכה
bracha. of מקדש השבת Mekadesh HaShabbat is a less common one. תדיר
ושאינו תדיר תדיר קודם. tadir vesheino tadir tadir kodem. And if you
have a common and a less common you do the more common.
So basically, while each one gave two reasons, we're going to focus
in on the reasons that are relevant to us. And the reasons
that are relevant to us is that בית הלל Beit Hillel says
you say the one that is more common first, בורא פרי הגפן,
Borei Peri HaGafen, and בית שמאי Beit Shammai says you say the
one that is more
distinctive—or at least that's the way they're reading בית שמאי—that Beit Shammai
the reason you say שבת Shabbat before בורא פרי הגפן Borei Peri
HaGafen is because שבת Shabbat is the reason you're saying קידוש, Kiddush,
which I would sort of say is the one that this is
the what makes this sort of all about. It's all about the
fact that it is שבת. Shabbat. So similarly is the we could
say that parallels the debate of סוכה sukkah, and שהחיינו. Shehecheyanu The
more common one first, or the one that more identifies the nature
of the day, סוכה sukkah. first. Okay. So let's take a look.
Of course so let's take a look what the גמרא Gemara. says.
Okay.
By the way you realize that our פסק psak is the reverse,
right? We say בורא פרי הגפן Borei Peri HaGafen first, which is
the more common one by קידוש, Kiddush. but we say שהחיינו Shehecheyanu
afterwards. So obviously the גמרא Gemara. is not going to stick with
the position that these are linked debates. Also it would have one
of the אמוראים going like בית שמאי. Beit Shammai. So let's take
a look what the גמרא Gemara says. לימא רב דאמר כבית שמאי?
leima Rav d'amar keBeit Shammai?
רב Rav who says that you say שהחיינו Shehecheyanu second is like
בית שמאי Beit Shammai that you say בורא פרי הגפן Borei Peri
HaGafen second? ורבה בר בר חנה דאמר שהחיינו veRabbah bar bar Chana
d'amar shehecheyanu first אמר כבית הלל? amar keBeit Hillel? Is like בית
הלל Beit Hillel that says you say בורא פרי הגפן Borei Peri
HaGafen first? אמר לך רב: amar lach Rav: רב Rav will tell
you, אנא דאמרי אפילו כבית הלל. ana d'amri afilu keBeit Hillel. I
am saying even according to בית הלל. Beit Hillel. עד כאן לא
קאמרי בית הלל התם אלא שהיין גורם לקידוש שתאמר. ad kan lo
ka'amri Beit Hillel hatam ela shehayayin goreim lekiddush sheteiamer.
Until now, when did בית הלל Beit Hillel say that you say
בורא פרי הגפן Borei Peri HaGafen first? Because you need the wine
to make it into קידוש. Kiddush. So the reason, the עיקר ikkar
reason of בית הלל Beit Hillel he's saying is not the idea
of תדיר. tadir. The עיקר ikkar reason, the primary—בית הלל Beit Hillel
gave two reasons—he threw in the reason of תדיר, tadir, but for
him the key reason is that wine makes it into קידוש. Kiddush,
אבל הכא, aval hacha, but here... אי לאו זמן ilav zman if
you weren't saying שהחיינו, Shehecheyanu מי לא אמרינן סוכה? me lo amrinan
sukka? Of course you would say לישב בסוכה and you'd sit in
the סוכה. sukkah. So the שהחיינו Shehecheyanu is not what makes it
into the מצוה mitzva of סוכה sukkah. or what allows you to
say the ברכה. bracha So he says, it's true, he gave two
reasons, and if you gave the reason of, you know, תדיר, tadir,
you would say שהחיינו Shehecheyanu first, but I don't believe that's the
real reason. I believe the real reason is because for קידוש, Kiddush,
יין yayin is what turns this into קידוש, Kiddush whereas here, it's
שהחיינו Shehecheyanu doesn't turn it into a מצוה mitzvah of sitting in
the סוכה sukkah. and therefore you say שהחיינו Shehecheyanu. second. And that's
actually the way we do it. רבה בר בר חנה אמר לך,
Rabba bar bar Chana amar lach, רבה בר בר חנה would say,
no, אנא דמיא אפילו בית שמאי, ana damya afilu Beis Shammai, I
who say you say שהחיינו Shehecheyanu first could say like בית שמאי
Beis Shammai that you do בורא פרי הגפן Borei Pri Hagafen last.
Because why, remember,
why do I say you say שהחיינו Shehecheyanu first? Because of תדיר.
tadir. But now I'm going to say, but I don't think בית
שמאי's Beis Shammai real reason is תדיר. tadir. עד כאן, Ad kan,
I mean excuse me, let's take a look. עד כאן לא אמרי
בית שמאי התם אלא שהיום גורם ליין שיבוא. Ad kan lo amri
Beis Shammai hasam ella sheyom gorem leyayin sheyavo. Why does בית שמאי
Beis Shammai say that you say מקדש השבת Mekadesh Hashabbos before בורא
פרי הגפן? Borei Pri Hagafen? Because the only reason you're doing the
קידוש Kiddush, and you're doing a בורא פרי הגפן Borei Pri Hagafen
is because it's שבת. Shabbos. אבל הכא, Aval hacha, here, אי לאו
סוכה מי לא אמרינן זמן? ilav sukkah mi lo amrinan zman?
If it weren't for סוכה sukkah. would we not say שהחיינו? Shehecheyanu
So he's saying look, remember I started by telling you שהחיינו Shehecheyanu
is doing double duty? So he's saying, you know what, in principle
what בית שמאי Beis Shammai says would map onto here. You start
with the idea of saying
of saying קידוש, Kiddush, of saying מקדש השבת, Mekadesh Hashabbos, and then
the יין yayin is sort of why you're doing this ritual and
why you start with the idea of the שבת Shabbos and then
שבת Shabbos is what makes you be doing קידוש, Kiddush then you
say בורא פרי הגפן. Borei Pri Hagafen. He says, but here, it's
not like if the שהחיינו, Shehecheyanu if the, excuse me, if the
שהחיינו Shehecheyanu was only about the מצוה mitzvah of סוכה, sukkah maybe
you'd be right. You start with סוכה sukkah. and that's the עיקר
ikkar and then you say the שהחיינו Shehecheyanu. which is the reason,
you know, it starts with the מצוה mitzvah of סוכה sukkah and
then שהחיינו Shehecheyanu, goes on it the same way it starts with
שבת Shabbos and the בורא פרי הגפן Borei Pri Hagafen goes on
it. But he says, you know, שהחיינו Shehecheyanu, has an independent significance.
שהחיינו Shehecheyanu. you're obligated to say even if you're not sitting in
a סוכה. sukkah שהחיינו Shehecheyanu is about like רש"י Rashi says, you
could be traveling on the road, not have a סוכה sukkah and
you'd still say שהחיינו Shehecheyanu because it's יום טוב. Yom Tov. So
therefore he says and if you combine the reasons, he's making a
powerful argument. He says, שהחיינו Shehecheyanu is תדיר. tadir. You say it
more commonly than סוכה. sukkah, And for tonight, it's not about sitting
in a סוכה, sukkah, it's about the חג, chag, but it's not
about sitting in the סוכה. sukkah. So this מצוה, mitzvah, this ברכה
of שהחיינו Shehecheyanu in a way precedes logically the sitting in a
סוכה. sukkah It's about the fact that it's the חג, chag it's
not linked to the sitting in the סוכה. sukkah. It's a more
common ברכה. Let's start with saying שהחיינו. Shehecheyanu So that is his
argument because it is not linked. The debate of בית הלל, Beis
Hillel, בית שמאי Beis Shammai about before after is because those two,
קידוש Kiddush. and מקדש השבת Mekadesh Hashabbos and בורא פרי הגפן Borei
Pri Hagafen are linked into the act of קידוש. Kiddush But here
he says, here people you should agree with my reason because not
only is it תדיר, tadir, but it's an independent ברכה and therefore
it should come first.
Yes, you have תנאים, Tannaim, they give two explanations for their position.
אמורא Amora comes along and says one of them's not true and
the other one's the other one. Right.
Yeah, he's not saying it's completely not true. I mean רש"י Rashi
and תוספות Tosafot both agree. He's sort of saying, yeah, there are
two reasons but obviously anytime you give two reasons, you know, the
question is like are they of equal weight, is one your primary
reason? So if you want to make your position work with another
one, you know, you're now you're saying, look, I can assume that
this one, you know, I could make my position work because maybe
this is the עיקר ikkar reason and not that. Okay, so now
you have it's very interesting. I mean the debate of בית הלל,
Beis Hillel, בית שמאי Beis Shammai in general is interesting and how
it links here why this would be different. And just again, if
you're sort of losing track of who's saying what, the עיקר ikkar
is that the idea of saying שהחיינו Shehecheyanu. first is really different
than that debate because שהחיינו Shehecheyanu has independent, is not just about
the מצוה mitzvah of sitting in a סוכה. sukkah, It's about the
חג chag and therefore is independent and if it's תדיר tadir maybe
it should come first. And the idea of saying it second, you
know, is very much because the
let me just again remember what the point was. Oh, right, because
because in a in a somewhat similar way also they're disconnected. It's
not like you need the שהחיינו Shehecheyanu in order to do the
מצוה mitzvah, of sitting in a סוכה. sukkah And therefore because סוכה
Sukkah. is more distinctive and is what the primary מצות היום mitzvas
hayom is, that should come first. So now we're going to see
if how it might debate, how it might connect. Clearly this was
a discussion we had to have in מסכת Masechet. סוכה, Sukkah okay,
but now we're going to see how it links to our משנה.
Mishnah So the גמרא Gemara says like this. תנן, Tenan, we taught
in our משנה. Mishnah, עצרת אומר לו הילך מצה הילך חמץ. Atzeret
omer lo heilach matzah heilach chametz. On שבועות they say to the
כהנים, Kohanim, here's your מצה matzah from the לחם הפנים Lechem Hapanim,
and here's your חמץ chametz, from the שתי הלחם. והכא דחמץ עיקר
מצה טפל. V'hacha d'chametz ikkar matzah tafel. Here חמץ chametz, is the
עיקר ikkar meaning it's mentioned first and מצה matzah is I'm sorry,
no, I said it wrong. חמץ chametz, is the עיקר ikkar in
the sense that it is שבועות is what is distinctive and מצה
matzah is
טפל. tafel. first. So that shows that we will prefer something that
is more common, you know, because of the תדיר tadir rule, over
something that is distinctive to the day, the חמץ. chametz So that
really the גמרא Gemara says boils down to what the debate is
about. We've admitted, both sides have said that it's not linked to
בית הלל Beit Hillel בית שמאי Beit Shammai because שהחיינו Shehecheyanu is
somewhat distinct from the מצוה mitzvah. sitting in a סוכה. Okay, so
they're somewhat distinct. So now we're back to the question: which one
comes first? So one argument is שהחיינו Shehecheyanu because it's תדיר, tadir,
and the other is סוכה because that's what the day is about
and it's more distinctive. So it says, so that's the debate, which
do you go by: תדיר tadir or what's distinctive? So it says
look, that's the case of מצה matzah and חמץ, and our משנה
Mishnah says you mention מצה matzah, first, you do the first one
first. תיובתא דרב, Tiyufta de-Rav, that's a contradiction to רב. Rav. אמר
לך רב תנאי היא, amar lecha Rav tanna'ei hi, it's a debate
of תנאים, Tannaim,
דתניא de-tanya because another ברייתא Beraita says הילך מצה והילך חמץ, heilei
matzah ve-heilei chametz, mentions מצה matzah first, not חמץ, I'm sorry, excuse
me, starts with our משנה, Mishnah, mentions מצה matzah, first and then
חמץ, אבא שאול אומר Abba Shaul omer in the ברייתא Beraita we
hear a dissenting view, אבא שאול: Abba Shaul: הילך חמץ והילך מצה,
heilei chametz ve-heilei matzah, starts with חמץ because that's more distinctive and
then goes to מצה, matzah. which is while it's more common, is
more generic. So that is exactly the debate, although רב Rav winds
up holding a minority position. Now, how are we going to rule?
Let's take a look, because as we are now רב Rav is
in the minority and we know that we actually do rule like
רב, Rav, but let's take a look. דרש רב נחמן בר רב
חסדא, darsha Rav Nachman bar Rav Chisda, לא כדברי רב דאמר סוכה
ואחר כך זמן, lo ke-divrei Rav de-amar sukkah ve-achar kach zman, we
don't go like רב, Rav, אלא זמן ואחר כך סוכה. ella zman
ve-achar kach sukkah. We go שהחיינו Shehecheyanu and then we say לישב
בסוכה. רב ששת בריה דרב אידי אמר: Rav Sheshet brei de-Rav Idi
amar: סוכה ואחר כך זמן. No, I'm sorry, you go like רב,
Rav, oh, he was of course בריה דרב, brei de-Rav, says you
say סוכה and then שהחיינו. Shehecheyanu והלכתא סוכה ואחר כך זמן, ve-hilchta
sukkah ve-achar kach zman, you say סוכה and then שהחיינו, Shehecheyanu like
you say לולב lulav and שהחיינו, Shehecheyanu like you say להדליק נר
של חנוכה, le-hadlik ner shel Chanukah, שהחיינו. Shehecheyanu
That's what we do. Of course, we sort of ignore the reason
that is on all those other cases of לולב lulav and חנוכה,
Chanukah, שהחיינו Shehecheyanu is not doing double duty, right? Even לולב lulav
during the day, it's not the שהחיינו Shehecheyanu for the יום טוב
Yom Tov because that you said last night, right? חנוכה Chanukah doesn't
have קדושת היום, kedushat hayom, you don't say שהחיינו Shehecheyanu for the
יום. So we've sort of said, okay, this follows the natural pattern,
שהחיינו Shehecheyanu follows the מצוה mitzvah, if the מצוה is the reason
you're saying it, although we should by the way note that there's
an irony there as well, because according to the ברייתא we learned
earlier and the עיקר הלכה, ikar halacha, you when you begin to
construct your לולב or construct your, you know, סוכה, you make a
שהחיינו Shehecheyanu there. But if you didn't do it when you were
making the object and you waited to the doing of the מצוה,
then you're going to say the ברכת המצוה first and then the
שהחיינו. Shehecheyanu So but what about the idea that is there is
some independence to the שהחיינו Shehecheyanu like we say שהחיינו Shehecheyanu in
קידוש Kiddush. on שבועות night? So that's why some people might be
aware of the complicated thing that goes on in the סידור siddur
about again, if you don't do it, you're still יוצא, yotze, and
not every סידור siddur says this, but it says that you say
you switch the order on the second day of יום טוב. Yom
Tov, Now why do we switch the order on the second day
of יום טוב Yom Tov, and say the שהחיינו Shehecheyanu before לישב?
So you could say, ah what we're trying to be nice, we're
trying to get every opinion in there. But that's not true normally,
we wouldn't bother and the גמרא Gemara specifically concluded that way. No,
it's because the dynamics change. By the second day יום טוב, Yom
Tov, the שהחיינו Shehecheyanu. is no longer doing double duty, right? Why
not? Because the שהחיינו you made on the סוכה, even in this
sort of ספיקא דיומא sefika de-yoma scenario that that first night wasn't
סוכות, Sukkot, but as I've been telling you, you can make a
שהחיינו on a new מצוה when you connect to the object of
the מצוה, like when you build the סוכה. So sitting in the
סוכה that first night even if it weren't theoretically יום טוב, Yom
Tov. even if it was like
building the סוכה. So by the second night, the שהחיינו that connects
to לישב בסוכה is no longer on the table. All you're left
with now is the שהחיינו that you made at קידוש. Kiddush. And
we make a שהחיינו second night יום טוב, Yom Tov right? Second
night, second night of שבועות, second night of פסח, Pesach, you make
a שהחיינו not related to any מצוה. So by the second night,
it's only it's not the שהחיינו of the מצוה, it's only the
שהחיינו of the קידוש. Kiddush, And since you start with the קידוש,
Kiddush, right? You say מקדש ישראל והזמנים, mekadesh Yisrael ve-hazmanim,
then you say the שהחיינו that goes with the קידוש, Kiddush. the
זמן, because that's the שהחיינו that goes with the קידוש. Kiddush. And
then after you're done with that, then you say לישב בסוכה. Okay,
so that's what that whole thing is about because by the second
night it is only the שהחיינו of the קידוש. But the first
night, where it's also the שהחיינו of the סוכה, we say you
start with the סוכה and then the שהחיינו like you say על
נטילת לולב al netilat lulav and שהחיינו and להדליק נר le-hadlik ner
and שהחיינו. So now you will know what the all what this
whole trick is about, you can you can impress your friends. Yes,
דוב? Dov?
Question about לחם הפנים. Lechem Hapanim. We often talk about it as
a hot, fresh loaf that stayed hot all week. Yeah. So do
we talk here about the מצה matzah. that was like a טפח
tefach thick?
Yeah, yeah, yeah. It was not the מצה, it's not the wafer
stuff we've got. The real, thick,
delicious מצה.
Exactly. Exactly. Okay, you just wanted to use this as an opportunity
for a push for Sephardic מצה. Okay, fine.
And I appreciate your saying that.
All right. So now we go to, we wrap this up. משמר
שזמנו קבוע ושאר קרבנות ציבור, Mishmar she-zmano kavua v'sha'ar korbanot tzibbur, so
it says things that are not unique to the חג chag other
than לחם הפנים Lechem HaPanim would not be divided equally. And therefore,
anything that you had other communal sacrifices other than the תמיד, Tamid,
the מוסף Musaf would be divided, that was unique, but the תמידים,
Tmidim, other private sacrifices, נדרים nedarim ונדבות, nedavot, that would all go
to the משמר mishmar whose week it actually was. And the משנה
Mishnah. ends by saying, and all other קרבנות ציבור korbanot tzibbur and
everything else. So what do those final phrases mean? ושאר קרבנות ציבור
לאתויי מאי, v'sha'ar korbanot tzibbur la'atuyei mai, what does that include? לאתויי
פר העלם דבר של ציבור ושעירי עבודת כוכבים, la'atuyei par he-alem davar
shel tzibbur u-se'irei avodat kochavim, you could have a communal sacrifice that's
not linked to the calendar when, you know, you have this situation
that the entire כלל ישראל Klal Yisrael sinned. The בית דין beit
din rules and everybody follows it incorrectly, they realize they ruled incorrectly,
or when the entire community does עבודה זרה, avoda zara, then there
are special communal sin offerings which are not linked to the calendar
and that would be the other thing we're including. Most of course
communal offerings are very much part of the calendar. והוא מקריב את
הכל, v'hu makriv et ha-kol, and you do everything. What's everything? לאתויי
מאי, la'atuyei mai, what does it include? לאתויי קיץ המזבח, la'atuyei kayitz
ha-mizbe'ach, the קיץ kayitz like the dessert of the מזבח mizbe'ach as
where רש"י Rashi says that means the summer vacation or whatever, but
the dessert of the מזבח mizbe'ach which means when there was very
often it speaks about, you know, if you had to redeem certain
animals and so on, the money would go לקיץ המזבח, l'kayitz ha-mizbe'ach,
the money would go to this generic קרבן korban fund on which
they would draw that if קרבנות korbanot, were not being brought, then
it would not look appropriate for the מזבח mizbe'ach to be there
with nothing going on, so they would draw on it in order
to bring these communal sacrifices, these communal עולות. olot. Okay, so that
would be the קיץ המזבח. kayitz ha-mizbe'ach. All right. So that would
be what would be how it would be divided on the חג
chag with the things that were unique to the חג chag, divided
by everyone. Okay. Now we take a look at what's going to
happen if it's almost a three-day יום טוב. Yom Tov They didn't
have three-day יום טוב Yom Tov except maybe for ראש השנה, Rosh
Hashanah, but they had something that came close. So let's take a
look. Next משנה, Mishnah, last משנה. Mishnah יום טוב הסמוך לשבת בין
מלפניה בין מאחריה. Yom Tov hasamuch l'shabbat bein milfaneha bein me-achareha. If
you have יום טוב Yom Tov that is next to שבת, Shabbat,
okay, which means that the יום טוב Yom Tov falls out, סוכות
Sukkot falls out on a Sunday, okay, or on a,
well, okay, it's going into the חג, chag, it's that סוכות Succot,
falls out on a Sunday, so therefore you had to come a
day before סוכות, Succot, you had to come on Friday. Or going
out of the חג, chag, סוכות Succot, falls out on Friday,
so you couldn't leave right afterwards, you had to stay over an
extra day.
It can't happen with the current calendar, but the exactly right. But
anyway, but the basic point is because שבת Shabbat either preceded or
followed the חג, you had to come a day early or leave
a day late. I'm going to come a day early or leave
a day late. So you're stuck in the בית המקדש Beit HaMikdash,
if you're a כהן, you're there an extra day, but it isn't
actually the רגל. reghel. So, but we're anyway all כהנים Kohanim had
to be here today. So do they have an equal participation in
the מקדש Mikdash on that preceding or following שבת? Shabbat? Let's take
a look. Okay, there's not going to be a lot of קרבנות,
korbanot it's only שבת. Shabbat. There's going to be the תמיד tamid
and the מוסף musaf and that's it. But okay, let's take a
look. And not a huge מוסף musaf either, שני כבשים. shnei kvashim.
All right. So יום טוב הסמוך לשבת בין מלפניה בין מאחריה היו
כל המשמרות שוות בחילוק לחם הפנים. Yom Tov hasamuch l'shabbat bein milfaneha
bein me-achareha hayu kol hamishmarot shavot b'chiluk Lechem Hapanim. So when it
came to the dividing of the לחם הפנים, Lechem HaPanim. as we
already learned, you know, that would be one of the things that
would be divided equally and there everybody would be the same. Now,
why it but presumably interestingly, you know, not for the תמיד tamid
and not for the מוסף musaf of שבת. Shabbat. And the logic
is because even on the רגל, reghel. when they were actually there
and supposed to be there, they would not equally divide, they would
not do the תמיד. tamid. The תמיד tamid was not distinctive to
the רגל. reghel. And the מוסף musaf is also not distinctive to
the רגל. Regel, So even if we acknowledge that you have to
be here, right, the you only get a portion of the קרבנות
korbanot that are distinctive to the רגל. So the שבת Shabbat portion,
שבת Shabbat afterwards, you're still out, you don't get anything. But what
you do get is לחם הפנים Lechem HaPanim because that was not
about being distinctive to the רגל. So since you had to be
here, you'll get a portion of the לחם הפנים, Lechem HaPanim? which
actually is exactly that extra day. שבת Shabbat is when you divide
the לחם הפנים. Lechem HaPanim Okay. So חל להיות יום אחד להפסיק
בינתיים, chale li-hiyot yom echad le-hafsik be-netayim, let's say it works out
that the יום טוב Yom Tov, is on Monday. So it's שבת,
Shabbat, Sunday, Monday. Or it's last day יום טוב Yom Tov is
Thursday and then Friday שבת. Shabbat. So it's like okay, who really
wants to be traveling in that... intervening day, especially if you don't
live nearby, you gotta, you gotta get home and like, you know,
just one, one day's travel, it's pretty hard. So therefore a lot
of people would come early in those or leave late in those
scenarios as well. Technically they didn't have to, but for practical reasons
that would happen a lot. So they also are somewhat expected to
be there, but somewhat at their discretion. So what portion would they
have of the לחם הפנים Lechem HaPanim, when it hit to when
it hit שבת? Shabbat? So, משמר שזמנו קבוע היה נוטל עשר חלות.
Mishmar shezmano kavoah hayah notel esser chalos. The fixed
משמר mishmar would get ten out of the twelve. Now actually it
means both the one leaving and the one coming in because they
would equally divide the לחם הפנים. Lechem HaPanim Okay, so right, לחם
הפנים Lechem HaPanim, you שבת Shabbos would be the changeover of the
changing of the guard, the old משמר mishmar to the new משמר,
mishmar, and basically the way it would work would be that they
would they would take all the twelve loaves and equally divide them,
we'll see in a minute equally or maybe a seven-five division, a
six-six division between the משמר mishmar that was leaving and the משמר
mishmar that was coming in. Okay, so those two משמרות mishmarot when
this happens get ten out of the twelve, not twelve but ten
out of the twelve, and the other two you give to the
כהנים Kohanim who decided to come early or stay late. והמתעכב, Vehamitakev,
and those extra כהנים Kohanim that stayed that that stayed
late or came early, you know, because of it was just one
day between שבת Shabbat and יום טוב, Yom Tov they get two
and they divide two amongst them. ובשאר ימות השנה, Uvshiar yemot hashana,
and right but the normal year, how would you divide לחם הפנים?
Lechem HaPanim. הנכנס נוטל שש והיוצא נוטל שש. Hanichnas notel shesh vehayotze
notel shesh. The משמר mishmar coming in would get half of the
breads and the משמר mishmar that would leaving would get half. רבי
יהודה אומר הנכנס נוטל שבע והיוצא נוטל חמש.
Rabbi Yehuda omer hanichnas notel
sheva vehayotze notel chamesh. No, the one coming in would get seven,
the one leaving would get five, we'll see why that is. הנכנסים
חולקין בצפון והיוצאים בדרום. Hanichnasim cholkin batzafon vehayotzim badarom. Now once we're
mentioning the difference between coming in and going out, the ones coming
in would would you know sit all together and divide up the
bread, they'd be sitting in the north part of the עזרה, Azara,
and those leaving in the south. The reason is that the north
is the holier part, the north is the more significant part, the
north is where right when you have a many קרבנות korbanot. has
to be שחט shachted על ירך המזבח צפונה al yerech hamizbeach tzafonah
on the north side of the מזבח. mizbeach. That's where you know
קדשי קדשים kodshei kodashim is all שחט shachted on the north side
of the מזבח. mizbeach. So therefore that's like a special status, you
could also say it's like a היכר heker to remind the ones
that are coming in, guys remember this is the more important side,
if you ever have a doubt where to שחט shacht the קרבן
korban do it here, okay, do it do it on the north,
but also because it's more important and that's where you שחט קדשי
קדשים shacht kodshei kodashim it's more status associated with it, so those
coming in were given the ones of greater were given the place
of greater status, those leaving were doing it in the south. בלגה,
Bilgah, which is one of the twenty-four משמרות, mishmarot, לעולם חולקת בדרום,
leolam choleket badarom, always even when it's coming in has to divide
up its bread in the south, וטבעתה קבועה, vetabaatah kevuah, its ring
where they would put the neck of the animal before they שחט
shachted or the place where they would שחט shacht all the animals
which was in the north and half of the עזרה, Azara, anyway
that would be closed up, it couldn't like, if you imagine like
you know a circular ring you know made out of metal and
you open it you open the latch and you put the neck
of the animal in and you close the latch, so if you
if you lock this, like I managed to do with my computer
right here, you can never you couldn't use it. So basically they
weren't able they had to שחט shacht the animals without the convenience
of using this ring. וחלונותיה סתומה, Vechalonoteha setumah, and its cubbyhole where
where they kept their knives was was sealed up, they got locked
they weren't entitled to have their own cubbyhole. So they obviously were
being punished for something and we will find out what in the
גמרא. Gemara It's quite fascinating, I don't know, somebody can give greater
explanation for this, why this מסכת, masechet. which is so much about
סוכות, Sukkot you know ends with א' לחם הפנים, Aleph Lechem HaPanim,
which is an interesting thing to be focusing on like what's the
connection of לחם lechem to סוכות, there's a לחם certainly connects much
more to פסח Pesach and שבועות than it does to סוכות, and
then to be ending with this like punishment here of this particular
section of the כהנים, Kohanim I don't know. But let's take a
look at the גמרא. Gemara מה לפניה ומה לאחריה? Mah lefaneha umah
leachareha? What does it mean if שבת Shabbos precedes or you know
juxtaposes to יום טוב Yom Tov immediately before and immediately after? אילימא
לפניה יום טוב הראשון, Ilema lefaneha Yom Tov harishon, if it means
that the first day יום טוב Yom Tov, came before שבת, Shabbat,
ולאחריה יום טוב האחרון veleachareha Yom Tov haacharon or the last day
of יום טוב Yom Tov came after שבת, Shabbat, היינו שבת שבתוך
החג, hainu Shabbat shebetoch hachag, that's crazy, then שבת Shabbat is during
the יום טוב, Yom Tov it's not a special case. אלא, Ela,
no, what it means is לפניה יום טוב האחרון, lefaneha Yom Tov
haacharon, that the last day of יום טוב Yom Tov came before
שבת, Shabbat, so then it was followed with שבת Shabbat and therefore
you couldn't go home on the immediate day following. ולאחריה, Veleachareha, or
יום טוב came after, יום טוב הראשון, Yom Tov harishon, the first
day of יום טוב came after שבת Shabbat so you had to
come a day early. Okay. מאי טעמא? Mai taama? Now what's the
reason that everybody divides equally? כיון דהני מקדמי והני מאחרי. Keivan dehani
makdemi vehani maachari. Since in those two cases you had to come
early, you had to come late, and you didn't have a choice,
you were stuck because of שבת, Shabbat, תיקנו רבנן מילתא כי היכי
דניחתו בהדי הדדי, Tikkunu rabbanan milta ke-hei de-neichu be-hadei hadadi, the rabbis
established something so that everybody should eat together. I like the phrase,
it doesn't just say so that you should be equally entitled to
the לחם הפנים Lechem HaPanim. because you're there, but the sense of
communal eating, that everybody should be eating together, you're all there, so
they wanted to make sure that there was, you know, not only
was it fair, but that everybody was eating together as a community.
Okay, חל יום אחד להפסיק בינתיים, Chal yom echad le-hafsik bein-tayim, if
there's a day's break, then you only get those people that decided
to come early or stay late, since in theory they could have,
they didn't have to be there that early, they only get two
loaves and everybody, and the other two major shifts of the כהנים
Kohanim, get ten. So the גמרא Gemara says, והני תרתי מאי עבידתייהו,
Ve-hanei tartei mai avidteihu, why are they being given the two loaves?
What they, I'm sorry, no, so that's not discussing that, I'm confusing
it here. So that's fine, the גמרא Gemara understands that it was
something that you gave, that you gave because they came early or
stayed late, end of that story. Now we move on to the
very end of the משנה, which is the regular division. The regular
division was six and six, when, you know, the two shifts were
changing of the guards, but according to רבי יהודה, Rabbi Yehuda, those
that were coming in got seven, and those that were leaving got
five. So why did he give more to those coming in than
those leaving? Why is there a difference of two loaves? Why is
those coming in get two extra loaves? I mean it's one extra,
but anyway, the division is, it's a difference of two. So והני
תרתי מאי עבידתייהו, Ve-hanei tartei mai avidteihu, what's the point of the
two extra loaves for the group coming in according to רבי יהודה?
Rabbi Yehuda? אמר רב יצחק בשכר הגפת דלתות, Amar Rav Yitzchak bis'char
hagafat delatot,
because they have to close the doors that were opened by the
group that was leaving. So the group was leaving opened the doors,
and now I gotta finish the job that you started, so which
is quite funny. Okay, you close the door, I open it, right?
But somehow it sort of speaks to the fact, I think it's
quite fascinating that like, you know, it's not my job. I, if
I had started it, I would close it, but you started it
and now I have to finish your job. So that somehow seemed
like extra work, okay? And because it's extra work, we get two
extra loaves. A tiny little extra work, comparable to what's going to
be going on the whole week, but let's take a look. The
גמרא Gemara goes on with this psychology. Okay, because of that they
get two extra. So the גמרא Gemara says, ונימא ליה דל בדל.
Ve-neima lei dal be-dal. Why not say, now what does this phrase
mean? It sort of means like tit for tat or it's all
in, it's all, you know, it all evens out in the end
is really what it means. רש״י Rashi says the word דל dal
means to remove, it gets removed from you, it gets removed from
me. רבנו חננאל Rabbeinu Chananel has I think a better explanation. דל
Dal does mean to remove, but
רבנו חננאל Rabbeinu Chananel says די לי ודי ליה di li ve-di
lei means belonging to me and belonging to you. So what he
says דל בדל dal be-dal means is, you know, whatever I get
you lose and whatever, and whatever you get I lose, in the
end it's all going to work out, right? By the end of
the week, I'm going to get five and the next group's going
to get seven. So why should I get seven now just to
lose it at the end of the next week? Let's just always
keep it at six. Okay, reasonable
explanation. So אמר אביי, Amar Abaye, בוצינא טבא מקרא, Butzina tava mikara,
so which is another idiom which basically translates as a bird in
the hand is worth two in the bush. בוצינא Butzina is a
small gourd type of a cucumber that ripens quickly, and קרא kara
is a large gourd that takes a long time to ripen. So
if you're told would you rather have this cucumber that's ripe now,
or would you rather wait a few weeks and you'll have a
much larger gourd? I'll take the cucumber now. So therefore the group
coming in, ah, why do you want seven now? On the way
out you're going to only get five. You know what, I'll worry
about that later, right now I want seven. So it's quite fascinating,
and obviously look, the difference between the amount of work closing the
doors for the ones that opened it is so trivial, but it's
part of I think the idea of giving status to those that
are coming in. You know, you've been there the whole week, you're
tired about a little bit or whatever, you're on your way out,
you want to sort of build up the excitement and the חשיבות,
chashivut, you know, and the sense of you're special, the group coming
in, you start, you give them, they go on the north, you
get an extra loaf, that seems to be the idea behind רבי
יהודה. Rabbi Yehuda. Dov, you wanted to say something?
Just, just accurate, like we have no way of knowing how many
כהנים kohanim. are in any given משמר. mishmar. You could be talking
about ten guys getting the seven, or we could be talking about
fifty guys getting, we're
talking about thousands, you know, in theory it's the entire population of
כהנים Kohanim divided by twenty-four.
It's not concrete, it's like we don't know
what we're talking about.
Right, exactly, exactly.
Okay. Exactly, we have no idea about what the numbers are. Exactly,
all right, fine. So, yes, one does really wonder that question, like
in practice, not just what was the population of the כהנים Kohanim,
or did they all come up לרגל, la-regel, but did all of
them actually, you know, were trained and practiced in the בית המקדש,
Beit Hamikdash, you know, was that somehow some subset? I mean reading
the גמרא Gemara it sounds like they're all supposed to be there
and they're all there, but you know, I don't know.
Maybe locally in the villages Maybe also in the villages they worked
out who was going to go this time or something?
I don't know. Okay, well, no, they're all supposed to be there
for the... Oh, you mean for that, not for the רגל, but
when it's your turn you're all supposed to show up. Yeah, whether
what really happened, I don't know. Okay. אמר רב יהודה, Amar Rav
Yehuda, says Rav Yehuda, ובמוספים חולקין. U'vemusafim cholkin. Now, on the מוסף,
Musaf, right, which is the same way they divide the group coming
in and the group going out, they divide the לחם הפנים, Lechem
HaPanim. they also divide the מוסף, Musaf, because they both were serving
today. One group, here's the point, the group that was there and
on its way out did the תמיד של שחר. Tamid shel Shachar.
The group that was coming in did the תמיד של בין הערביים.
Tamid shel bein ha'arbayim. So one was the morning shift and then
the other was the afternoon shift. How about the מוסף? Musaf? Okay,
now the מוסף Musaf is normally more associated with the morning, but
he says that they divided the מוסף. Musaf. So the גמרא Gemara
says like this, מיתיבי, Meisivei, an objection is raised, משמרה היוצאת, Mishmarah
hayotzeis, the leaving משמרה, Mishmarah, עושה תמיד של שחר ומוספים. Osah Tamid
shel Shachar u'musafim. They would do the morning תמיד Tamid and the
מוסף, Musaf, which normally is bundled with the morning. משמרה הנכנסת, Mishmarah
hanichneses, and the one entering
in, עושה תמיד של בין הערביים ובזיכין. Osah Tamid shel bein ha'arbayim
u'vazichin. The בזיכין vazichin were the little cup spoons of
incense, frankincense, that was offered up on the מזבח Mizbeach to allow
the לחם הפנים Lechem HaPanim, to be eaten. Okay, so they would
actually offer that up. That was seen as more of an afternoon
עבודה. Avodah, ואילו מוספים חולקין לא קתני. Ve'ilu musafim cholkin lo katani.
So it doesn't say that they divide the מוסף. Musaf. It says
the מוסף Musaf was done by the morning group. So the גמרא
says, אמר רב יהודה, Amar Rav Yehuda, when I said חולקין, cholkin,
that they divide it, במאי? be'mai? In what way do they divide
it? בעורות, Be'oros, the skins. So, and now it acknowledges that this
is talking about who does the עבודה, Avodah, not who benefits from
it. Again, מוסף Musaf is on שבת, Shabbos,
it's עולות, Olos, there's not even a חטאת Chatas to eat, but
you still question about like who gets the skin. So there would
be some benefit that you would divide. So this משנה is talking
about who gets to do the עבודה, Avodah but the assumption is
is that who benefits from the עבודה Avodah as well is linked
to who did it. And it doesn't say that they would divide
the skin of the מוסף. Musaf. Okay, so the גמרא says no,
האי תנא בחלוקה לא קא מיירי. Hai tanna be'chalukah lo ka mairy.
It's not talking about who gets the benefit and dividing what's left
over. It's talking about who does the offering. I acknowledge the morning
משמר Mishmar brings the מוסף, Musaf, but I say that they equally
divide the leather, the skin of the מוסף. Musaf. אמר רבא, Amar
Rava, so Rava says, והתנא דבי שמואל דמיירי בחלוקה, Ve'ha tanna devei
Shmuel de'mairy be'chalukah, I will show you a תנא tanna from the
house of שמואל Shmuel that addresses the question of how things are
divided, meaning not just the עבודה Avodah. but the things you get
from the עבודה. Avodah ובמוספים חולקין לא קתני, U'vemusafim cholkin lo katani,
and does not say they would divide the מוסף. Musaf. דתנא דבי
שמואל, De'tanna devei Shmuel, we taught in the house of
שמואל, Shmuel, משמרה היוצאת, Mishmarah hayotzeis, the leaving משמרה, Mishmarah, עושה תמיד
של שחר ומוספים. osah Tamid shel Shachar u'musafim. משמרה הנכנסת, Mishmarah hanichneses,
the one coming
in, עושה תמיד של בין הערביים ובזיכין. osah Tamid shel bein ha'arbayim
u'vazichin. ארבעה כהנים היו נכנסים שם. Arba'ah Kohanim hayu nichnasim sham.
Now, how would they do the removal of the bread? This is
actually very nice because they divide the לחם הפנים, Lechem HaPanim also
parallel to that, they had both groups working together. There was like
a joint participation in the actual service related to the bread. How
does this
work? ארבעה כהנים נכנסים שם, Arba'ah Kohanim nichnasim sham, four כהנים, Kohanim,
שנים ממשמר זו ושנים ממשמר זו, shnayim mi'mishmar zu u'shnayim mi'mishmar zu,
two from each משמרה, Mishmarah, the one coming in and the one
leaving, וחולקין לחם הפנים, ve'cholkin Lechem HaPanim, and they divide the לחם
הפנים. lechem hapanim, So what it doesn't fully spell out was
the way they would do it would be basically, it would be
like a table
which had shelves, but it was open at both ends. And you'd
have the new bread and the old bread, and you would be
putting in the new as somebody on the other side was taking
out the old. Okay, and that was sort of done in this
partnership with the new group and the old group appropriately. You know,
come in the new and go out the old, but at least
it was done in partnership. And that parallels very nicely that they
would divide the לחם הפנים. Here they are coming and going out,
they do one thing together. But it talks about the dividing of
the לחם הפנים. It does discuss who gets
it. ובמוספים חולקין לא קתני. U'vemusafim cholkin lo katani. It so it's
discussing not only who does the עבודה Avodah, but who benefits from
it, and it does not say that they would divide the מוסף.
Musaf. תיובתא דרב יהודה תיובתא. Tiyuvta de'Rav Yehuda tiyuvta. That is a
full contradiction of רב יהודה. Rav Yehuda. Clearly they would not divide
the מוסף. Musaf. So each group would do their appropriate עבודה, avoda
but for the לחם הפנים, there would actually be an overlap in
the taking out and the putting in as there was an overlap
in the group, as there was like a participation or a joint
participation of both groups, they would divide the לחם הפנים equally as
well. Okay, so now it says like
this, תנו רבנן. Tanu Rabbanan. Now רש"י Rashi by the way asks
the question, what even was the הוה אמינא hava amina that they
would get a part? of the מוסף Musaf if it was brought
by the morning משמר? mishmar? And Rashi says, well, because again talking
about leftover things, that sort of leftover work to do, the ones
that are coming in the afternoon might have to still sort of
fit, rotate the meat on the fire of the מזבח, mizbeiach, stuff
that wasn't burned, push it back on the fire pile and so
on. So there still was some wrapping up what was done earlier.
But nevertheless, it was basically an עבודה avoda, of the first group,
and they got the benefit, they got the skin, but the לחם
הפנים, which was a joint עבודה, avodah, they equally divided. Okay, תנו
רבנן. Tanu Rabbanan. הנכנסים חולקים בצפון כדי שיראו שהן נכנסים. Ha-nichnasin cholkin
bitzafon kedei she-yeira’u she-hein nichnasin. The ones coming in have a distinctive
place, so it's clear that they're coming in. Not that north means
coming in, but once that becomes their designated space, then it becomes
obvious who's the group going in and who's the group going out.
היוצאים חולקים בדרום כדי שיראו שהן יוצאים. Ha-yotzin cholkin bidarom kedei she-yeira’u
she-hein yotzin. Okay, again, to sort of make it clear who's coming
in and who's leaving, and there's no sort of confusion about that.
So maybe we have some participation, but we also have that we're
keeping the identities distinct. Now we get to בלגה, Bilgah, which is
the very fascinating way of ending the מסכת. בלגה לעולם חולקת בדרום.
Bilgah le-olam choleket bidarom. בלגה, Bilgah, even when it's coming in, gets
to be in, has to be in the south. תנו רבנן. Tanu
Rabbanan. Now we're going to hear some of the
background. מעשה במרים בת בלגה, Maaseh be-Miriam bat Bilgah, story of מרים
Miriam the daughter of בלגה, Bilgah, obviously not the daughter of בלגה
Bilgah when this thing started, this was in the middle of the
בית שני Bayit Sheini period, the division of the משמרות mishmarot was
way back in בית ראשון. Bayit Rishon. So anyway, but it means
she was from
those כהנים. She was from the משמר, mishmar, her that was her
family was in the משמר mishmar of בלגה. Bilgah. שהמירה דתה, She-himira
datah, and she actually became an apostate, she rejected Judaism. This was
in the period of the יוונים. Yevanim. She went and she identified
with Hellenism and the Greeks. והלכה וניסת לסרדיוט אחד ממלכי יוונים, Ve-halcha
ve-nisset le-sardyot echad mi-malchei Yevanim,
and she went and married one of the
Greek
soldiers, I think this is what it means. What does Steinsaltz say?
Soldier. Okay, a soldier in the Greek army,
officer, thank you, an officer in the Greek army. כשנכנסו יוונים להיכל,
Keshe-nichnesu Yevanim le-heichal,
now of course look, this is reflecting a reality, you know, we
always talk about the Greeks being the bad guys, the Seleucids being
the bad guys in the חנוכה Chanukah story, which they were, but
we ignore the fact that there were tons of Hellenizers as well,
Hellenizing Jews. And a lot of the fighting was not just between
the Jews and the Greeks, it was between the פרום frum Jews
and the Hellenizing Jews if you would. So she actually was siding
with the Hellenizing Jews and when the Greeks came in she was
thrilled with it. Let's get rid of this religion and this tribal
religion and let's all be part of the Greek world. So כשנכנסו
יוונים להיכל, keshe-nichnesu Yevanim le-heichal, when the Greeks entered in in the
pre-חנוכה Chanukah story into the Temple, היתה מבועטת בסנדלה על גבי המזבח.
hayata meva'atet be-sandalah al gabei ha-mizbeiach.
So she would kick with her sandal the altar. ואמרה לו Ve-amerat
lo and say to it, לוקוס לוקוס, Lukus Lukus, wolf, wolf, right,
לוקוס, Lukus, עד מתי אתה מכלה ממונם של ישראל, ad matai atah
mechaleh mamonam shel Yisrael, how long will you be consuming the Jewish
wealth, property? Because they're all bringing all their קרבנות. ואי אתה עומד
להם בשעת הדחק, Ve-i atah omeid lahem be-sha'at hadechak, and you're not
there to defend them when they're being
attacked. So she was also rationalizing her decision to abandon Judaism. כששמעו
חכמים בדבר, Keshe-shamu chachamim badavar,
when they heard this, not only okay, sometimes there were Hellenists, but
the fact that she was doing this public act of defiance and
disgrace, so קבעו את טבעתה, kave'u et taba'atah, they made this, this,
they penalized the entire משמר mishmar of בלגה. Bilgah. They fixed its
ring that it couldn't use it for the שחיטה. shechitah. וסתמו את
חלונה, Ve-satmu et chalonah, and they closed up its cubby hole. ויש
אומרים, Ve-yeish omrim, so that's why, that's one version of the story.
ויש אומרים, Ve-yeish omrim, there's another version of why they were penalized.
משמרתו שהיה לו לבוא ונכנס ישבב אחיו עמו ושמש תחתיו. Mishmarto she-hi-lo
lavo ve-nichnas Yeshevav achiv immo ve-shimeish tachtav. There was one שבת Shabbos
where they basically weren't showing up for work. No, where, where's בלגה?
Bilgah? It's their turn. No בלגה Bilgah people weren't around. So ישבב
Yeshevav who was from the previous week had to stay late and
had to do the work that בלגה Bilgah was supposed to do.
So that's why, it showed that they did not respect their own
fully their responsibility and
therefore,
they were penalized from that time onwards. Okay, ושמש
תחתיו. ve-shimeish tachtav. אף על פי שששכני הרשעים לא נשתכרו, Af al
pi she-sh'cheinie hara'im lo nistakaru, normally we say that those that dwell
with nearby neighbors of wicked people don't benefit, and we're just going
to be a principle of אוי לרשע אוי לשכנו, oy l'rasha oy
l'shcheino, normally they suffer with the bad things that happen to the
wicked people. Nevertheless, שכני בלגה נשתכרו, sh'cheinie Bilgah nistakaru, those that lived
close to בלגה Bilgah as it were, ישבב, Yeshevav, the משמר mishmar
that came before, benefited. שבלגה לעולם חולקת
בדרום וישבב אחיו בצפון. She-Bilgah le-olam choleket bidarom ve-Yeshevav achav bitzafon. Right?
You get it? If בלגה Bilgah even when they come in are
in the south, that means the group that was there beforehand gets
the benefit of being in the north not only when they come
in. but even when they go, right? So now that makes sense
if ישובב Yeshevev were the ones that had to cover for בילגה.
Bilga. So they get this indirect benefit of בילגה Bilga is always
being penalized vis-a-vis them. Okay, so the גמרא says like this: בשלמא
למאן דאמר משמרתו שהיה לו לבוא, Bishlama leman de'amar mishmarto shehaya lo
lavo, if you say the entire משמרה, mishmarah, you know, was sort
of irresponsible and they didn't show, and maybe this was an ongoing
problem, let's assume that makes it easier to understand why they're being
constantly have this penalty associated to them. So היינו דקנסינן לכולה משמר.
hainu dekanisnan lechulah mishmar. But the גמרא is not only concerned about
why it's a long-term קנס knas as opposed to a temporary one,
but it's concerned with who are you
penalizing? So if the entire group was irresponsible, then everybody's going to
get penalized. Okay. אלא למאן דאמר מרים בת בילגה שהמירה דתה, ella
leman de'amar Miriam bat Bilga shehemira datah, but if it was one
person, מרים, Miriam, who, who, you know, rebelled and who became an
apostate, משום ברתא, mishum barta, because of his daughter—again, it's so funny
it does it in a singular, it's not like one person, you
know, not בילגה's Bilga daughter—but okay. Anyway, but because of one person
קנסינן לדידיה, kansinan ledideih, we're going to fine the entire, the entire
משמרה mishmarah
of בילגה? Bilga? Is that fair? So what are you—collective punishment, it's
not fair! It's what my kids say in school when, you know,
okay, the whole class is going to stay late, what's collective punishment,
that's not fair. So אמר אביי אין, amar Abaye in, yeah, tough
luck, sometimes you do have collective punishment, הינאמי אינשי, hainami inshi, as
people say, שותא דינוקא, shuta de'yanuka, and here's why, because it's not
just one person's responsibility, the community is responsible as well. Okay, how
is the community responsible? Because people will say the babbling, like the,
you know, the casual talk of a child, בשוקא, beshuka, that he'll
talk in the marketplace, אבוה או דאמיה, avuha o de'imeih,
he's got to pick it up from somewhere, right? Where did he
learn to talk that way? Where did he learn to talk about
those things? Where did he get those ideas from? Must have come
from the house. So as we all know as parents and when,
when we're like sort of, you know, and when we're, you know,
and our kids say
something that we're like, I can't believe he just said that in
public, that's where other people are. Anyway, so sometimes it's true, sometimes
it's not true, there also's a playground and other places where they
pick things up. But okay, says how does somebody—now the point is
maybe רש"י says it's not true that like every time somebody went
ahead and, you know, sinned or became an apostate we say, oh,
you know, they got that idea from their upbringing. But the idea
not just that she made that type of a choice, but to
disgrace, you know, to, which she, you know, the way she like
degraded the מזבח, mizbe'ach, destroying the money of ישראל, Yisrael, so that's
like an attitude that must have come, you know, from amongst a
group of כהנים and their feelings about what does the temple service
mean. So that's where it's saying that that clearly was something that
came from, from the home and therefore, of course, the home, again,
you know, it's one group of כהנים, one family, there's an entire
משמרה mishmarah which is hundreds of כהנים, hundreds of families or thousands
of families, but nevertheless, there was a feeling that these must be
some attitudes that are prevalent in this משמרה mishmarah or else where
else would she have picked it up.
Yes, what's the last word?
שותא. shuta. שותא shuta just means like the babbling, the, you know...
Does it literally be the verb that means to talk?
The talking, yeah, the talk. It's a noun, but it means like
the, the speech, but not—but you know, but almost like casual speech.
So the גמרא says, ומשום אבוה ואימיה קנסינן לכולה משמר,
u'mishum avuha
ve'imeih kansinan lechulah mishmar,
so now the גמרא asks: fine, so in that family they obviously,
you know, did not, you know, spoke, you know, had negative attitudes
towards the עבודה, towards the מזבח, mizbe'ach, that would be the family,
but we're going to fine the entire משמרה? mishmarah? So אמר אביי
אוי לרשע אוי לשכינו, amar Abaye oi lerasha oi lishcheno,
woe to the enemy—woe to the evil person and woe to his
neighbor. Sometimes you get, so you get, you get caught in the
crossfire, which is interesting, meaning so there's an aspect of collective punishment
which is deserved because sometimes, you know, the community is also responsible
for certain ways in which the individual acts, and sometimes as the
broader community it's not deserved, but you know what, you have to
suffer as a result. You know, there's also obviously a benefit to
that, which means that from here on in the community is going
to try to exert its pressure to make sure that these types
of things don't happen in
the
future. אוי לרשע אוי לשכינו טוב לצדיק טוב לשכינו. oi lerasha oi
lishcheno tov latzaddik tov lishcheno. שנאמר אמרו צדיק כי טוב כי פרי
מעלליהם יאכלו. shene'emar imru tzaddik ki tov ki pri ma'alaleihem yocheilu. The
צדיק tzaddik says that it's good because the fruit of their deeds—presumably
the דקדוק dikduk is going from the singular צדיק tzaddik to the
מעלליהם, ma'alaleihem, the plural—they will eat. Multiple people, not just the צדיק,
tzaddik, but even those that are near the צדיק. tzaddik. So it's
good to stick with a, you know, good חברא chevra and good
community and you'll benefit from them as opposed to sticking with those
or nearby those that are not. הדרן עלך החליל וסליקא לך מסכת
סוכה. hadran alach hachalil u'selika lach Masechet Sukkah. Again, I do not
know what to make about this as the ending of the מסכת.
I wish I could say something that would be tie it in
nicely, but anyway, this is the best I can start thinking
about is that sense of, you know, we sort of the there
was a theme of house of בית bayit that was very prevalent
of course in סוכה. I will also say one thing that I
wanted to say before which was, you know, we mentioned the amount
of talking that gets done sort of towards the the בית המקדש,
Beit Hamikdash you know, during this time. Like, you know, when they're
doing the ערבה aravah as they say, you know, they say, what
do they say? יופי לך מזבח, yofi lach mizbe'ach, you know, יופי
לך מזבח yofi lach mizbe'ach when they're walking out after the to
do the ניסוך המים nisuch hamayim they turn around and they say
אנו ליה ועינינו ליה, anu l'Ya v'eineinu l'Ya, right, so and then
we had the whole story of הלל Hillel and הלל Hillel was
almost like speaking doing the other side in dialogue. He was speaking
for God: אם אני כאן הכל כאן, im ani kan hakol kan,
right? So there's a lot of this like dialogue that we never
have talking to the בית המקדש Beit Hamikdash or and here you
have מרים Miriam doing the same thing, she's talking to the altar.
So that's I think a fascinating thing about that talking that gets
done. Maybe it somehow has to do again with this sense of
the whole סוכות about being about being in God's house and bringing
God into our house, so being in the presence of someone and
that intimacy that comes in the presence of a house is about
this sense of dialogue and conversation. Maybe that's why some of this
is getting verbalized. And maybe also that's why it ends, this is
just a דרוש, drush, I don't know if it really works, but
maybe also that's why it ends a little bit with sometimes, you
know, families have problems too.
And you're there in the house and maybe, you know, and maybe
things don't always, you know, don't work out so well and there
you have to be responsible for everybody in the house. There's a
real reality that sets in when you're leaving the בית המקדש Beit
Hamikdash and you're leaving your סוכה and going back into your house.
But the reality is that even in the בית המקדש it wasn't
always so פשוט pashut and some of those types of dynamics were
present as well. Okay, so tomorrow we will begin מסכת ביצה. Masechet
Beitzah. Does anybody say קדיש?
Kaddish?